<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Heng Li's blog</title>
 <link href="http://lh3.github.io/blog/" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://lh3.github.io/blog"/>
 <updated>2014-07-05T01:39:42-04:00</updated>
 <id>http://lh3.github.io/blog</id>
 <author>
   <name>Heng Li</name>
   <email>lh3@me.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>My blog</title>
   <link href="http://lh3.github.io/blog/2014/07/05/my-blog"/>
   <updated>2014-07-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://lh3.github.io/blog/2014/07/05/my-blog</id>
   <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;I have a &lt;a href=&quot;http://lh3lh3.users.sourceforge.net&quot;&gt;homepage&lt;/a&gt;. It is using a CSS template heavily modified from a
theme from &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_Page_Creator&quot;&gt;Google Pages&lt;/a&gt;, which has long been discontinued. This
template has been used for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://samtools.sourceforge.net&quot;&gt;SAMtools website&lt;/a&gt; among a few others.
I still like the general look-and-feel of the template, but I do have a few
concerns with my homepage. Firstly, I do not like to write raw HTML, as is
opposed to MarkDown. Secondly, as a novice web developer, I still have troubles
with fine tuning the CSS template. Thirdly and most importantly, I am unable to
get feedbacks from readers. While there are services like &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com&quot;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt;, I
am too lazy to learn how to integrate them. After all, I am a scietific
researcher. Due to these concerns, I have not updated my homepage often in the
past few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I sometimes feel it is necessary to describe my preliminary
works and express my immature thoughts in short articles. Maybe some of them
could be useful to others as well. Blog posts seem a good way to achieve the
goal. This is why I started this blog. I do not know where it goes or if I will
update often, but a little bit more documentation is better than nothing, I
believe.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>